谎言的代价是什么
What is the cost of lies?
切尔诺贝利
前情提要
该责怪谁
Who is to blame?
也无所谓
It doesn't matter.
看起来不对劲
It doesn't look right.
我们尝到金属味儿了
We taste metal.
我认为地上有石墨
I think there's graphite on the ground.
你没有看到石墨
You didn't see graphite.
你没看到  因为根本没有
You didn't because it's not there!
我们封锁城市  以防消息的误传
We seal off the city. Contain the spread of misinformation.
米哈伊尔·戈尔巴乔夫总书记设立了一个委员会
Secretary Gorbachev has appointed a committee
来处理事故  你也是其中一员
to manage the accident. You're on it.
切尔诺贝利
第二集
明斯克  白俄罗斯核能源研究所
4月26日  上午8点30分
爆炸发生7小时后
你工作太不要命了
You work too hard.
-其他人呢  -他们都不肯来
- Where is everyone? - Oh, they refused to come in.
-为什么  -因为今天是周六
- Why? - It's Saturday.
-那你怎么来了  -我也工作不要命
- Why did you come in? - I work too hard.
这里好热
It's boiling in here.
8毫伦琴  是泄露吗
Eight milliroentgen. A leak?
不
No.
不然早响了  是外面飘进来的
It would've gone off before. It's coming from outside.
美国人吗
The Americans?
原创翻译  双语字幕
最新连载海外影视剧下载
请登陆 www.YYeTs.com
仅供交流学习  禁止商用盈利
翻译    草草  Eunice  elingbow  DerbyNinja
翻译     白夜君  哈里不是波特  babibada
翻译     tong大梨  放开那个方丈  小酸奶
顾问     elingbow
校对     草草  苏葵
时间轴     荞麦麦  Caroline
后期     8T  拉图
总监     苏葵
碘131
Iodine 131.
不是军用  是铀衰变  铀235
It's not military. It's uranium decay, U-235.
反应堆燃料
Reactor fuel?
可能是伊格纳利纳  离我们大概240公里
Ignalina. Maybe, uh, 240 kilometers away.
我是乌拉娜·霍缪克
Yes, this is Ulana Khomyuk
我们是白俄罗斯核能...
with the Institute of Nuclear En--
找...
Looking for--?
-好吧  冷静点  -别叫我冷静
- All right, stay calm. - Don't tell me to stay calm.
他们那儿才4毫伦琴  不是他们
They're at four. It's not them.
接下来最近的是谁
Who's the next closest?
切尔诺贝利  但那不可能
It's Chernobyl, but that's not possible.
他们离我们400公里呢
They're 400 kilometers away.
那么远不会有8毫伦琴飘过来
That's too far for eight milliroentgen.
除非是反应堆暴露在外
They'd have to be split open.
或许他们知情
Maybe they know something.
-碘片  -会是废料倾倒吗
- Iodine. - Could it be a waste dump?
不会
No.
那该有其他同位素
We'd be seeing other isotopes.
核测试  新式炸弹
Nuclear test? Uh, new kind of bomb?
那我们肯定能听说  这里半数人就干这个
We'd have heard. That's what half our people work on here.
会不会是太空计划  卫星什么的
Something with the space program like a satellite or...?
没人接听
No one's answering the phone.
-给所有人打点滴  -点滴不够了
- Get everyone started on an IV. - We don't have enough.
-那就儿童优先  -那也不够
- All the children then. - But we don't have enough!
那就有多少打多少
As many as you can.
-老头子呢  -他在16室设立了烧伤病房
- Where's the old man? - He's set up a burn ward in 16.
你干什么呢  那是什么
What are you doing? What is that?
牛奶  是牛奶  比水好使
Milk. It's milk. Much better than water.
不不  快停下
No, no, no. Stop. Stop!
-你干什么  -这是辐射烧伤
- What are you doing? - These are radiation burns!
他们的衣服都污染了
Their clothes are contaminated!
帮我
Help me!
都脱掉
Get it all off.
拿去地下室
We're taking it down to the basement.
他是切尔诺贝利的消防员
He was a firefighter from Chernobyl.
你能不能别推了
Can you stop pushing, please?
我们有命令
We have our orders!
-回去吧  -抓住他
- Disperse! - Hey, there! Get him!
你们为什么不让我们进
Why you keeping us out here?
列加索夫教授
Professor Legasov?
不  还没到时候
Oh, no, not yet.
他们还在处理其他事
They're finishing up some other business.
还得要几分钟
It'll be a few more minutes.
-要给您端点茶吗  -不了  谢谢
- Can I get you some tea? - No, I'm fine. Thank you.
您等的时候
Would you care to read
想看看谢比纳副主席的报告吗
Deputy Chairman Shcherbina's report while you wait?
太好了  谢谢
Certainly. Thank you.
好了  教授  你可以进去了
All right, Professor. They're ready.
列加索夫教授
Professor Legasov?
我会支持你
You have my support.
谢谢各位为本委员会尽责
Thank you all for your duty to this commission.
我们先听取谢比纳副主席的报告
We will begin with Deputy Chairman Shcherbina's briefing,
然后  如有必要  再讨论接下来的行动
and then we will discuss next steps if necessary.
谢谢  总书记同志
Thank you, comrade General Secretary.
我很高兴地汇报
I'm pleased to report
切尔诺贝利的情况已稳定了下来
that the situation in Chernobyl is stable.
军事和平民巡逻队已确保了当地安全
Military and civilian patrols have secured the region,
皮卡洛夫大将
and Colonel General Pikalov,
率领着专业处理化学性公害的军队
who commands troops specializing in chemical hazards,
也已被派遣到核电站
has been dispatched to the plant.
就辐射而言  核电站厂长布卡诺夫报告
In terms of radiation, plant director Bryukhanov
辐射量不超过3.6伦琴
reports no more than 3.6 roentgen.
我被告知辐射量相当于一次胸透
I'm told it's the equivalent of a chest X-ray.
所以如果你很久没做体检了...
So if you're overdue for a check-up...
-外国媒体呢  -毫不知情
- And foreign press? - Totally unaware.
克格勃第一副主席佘考夫向我保证
KGB First Deputy Chairman Charkov assures me
我们已成功保护了我方安全利益
that we have successfully protected our security interests.
很好  非常好
Good. Very good.
看来我们已经控制了局势
Well, it seems like it's well in hand, so...
如果没其他事的话  休会
if there's nothing else, meeting adjourned.
不
No!
你说什么
Pardon me?
不能休会
Uh, we can't adjourn.
这位是库尔恰托夫研究所的列加索夫教授
This is Professor Legasov of the Kurchatov Institute.
教授  你有疑问的话
Professor, if you have any concerns,
可以晚点跟我说
feel free to address them with me later.
不行  抱歉  很抱歉
I can't. I am sorry. I'm so sorry.
第三页  人员伤亡部分
Page three, the section on casualties.
"一位消防员在反应堆厂房外
"A fireman was severely burned on his hand
被地上一大块表面光滑的黑色矿物
"By a chunk of smooth, black mineral on the ground,
严重烫伤了手"
outside the reactor building."
表面光滑的黑色矿物  是石墨
Smooth, black mineral-- graphite.
地上有石墨
There's-There's graphite on the ground.
发生了水箱爆炸  导致现场有碎片
Well, there was a... A tank explosion. There's debris.
那能有多重要...
Of what importance that could be--?
整个核电站只有一个地方
There's only one place in the entire facility
有石墨  那就是堆芯里面
where you will find graphite: inside the core.
如果外面地上有石墨
If there's graphite on the ground outside,
就意味着爆炸的不是控制系统水箱
it means it wasn't a control system tank that exploded.
而是反应堆芯  它被炸开了
It was the reactor core. It's open!
谢比纳同志
Um, Comrade Shcherbina?
总书记同志  我向你保证
Comrade General Secretary, I can assure you
列加索夫教授弄错了
that Professor Legasov is mistaken.
布卡诺夫说反应堆芯完好无损
Bryukhanov reports that the reactor core is intact.
-至于辐射量...  -没错  3.6伦琴
- And as for the radiation-- - Yes, 3.6 roentgen,
顺便说一下  这并不等于一次胸透的辐射量
which, by the way, is not the equivalent of one chest X-ray,
而是相当于四百次
but rather 400 chest X-rays.
不过我不是因为这个原因感到不安
That number's been bothering me for a different reason, though.
这也是低精度剂量计的量程上限
It's also the maximum reading on low-limit dosimeters.
他们只上报了手里有的数值
They gave us the number they had.
我认为真正的数值远比那高
I think the true number is much, much higher.
如果我没弄错  这位消防员手中拿着
If I'm right, this fireman was holding the equivalent
相当于四百万次胸透的辐射量
of four million chest X-rays in his hand.
列加索夫教授  不要危言耸听  歇斯底里
Professor Legasov, there's no place for alarmist hysteria--
如果这是事实  就不是危言耸听
It's not alarmist if it's a fact!
我完全没听到什么事实
Well, I don't hear any facts at all.
我只听到一个我不认识的人
All I hear is a man I don't know
妄加臆测
engaging in conjecture
且所说的与党官员所报告的内容截然相反
in direct contradiction to what has been reported by party officials.
我  我很抱歉
I'm, uh... I apologize.
我不是想...
I didn't mean, uh...
能否允许我
Please, may I express my concern
冷静且尊敬地表达我的担忧
as calmly and as respectfully as I--
-列加索夫教授  -鲍里斯
- Professor Legasov-- - Boris.
让他说
I will allow it.
RBMK反应堆
An RBMK reactor
使用铀235作为燃料
uses uranium 235 as fuel.
铀235每个原子都像一颗
Every atom of U-235 is like a bullet
以接近光速射出的子弹
traveling at nearly the speed of light,
能穿透所经之处的一切事物
penetrating everything in its path:
木头  金属  水泥  肉体
woods, metal, concrete, flesh.
每一克铀235中
Every gram of U-235 holds
有10的21次方颗这种子弹
over a billion trillion of these bullets.
一克而已
That's in one gram.
而切尔诺贝利的装载量有三百多万克
Now, Chernobyl holds over three million grams,
现在正在燃烧
and right now, it is on fire.
放射性粒子会随风
Winds will carry radioactive
散布到整个大陆
particles across the entire continent,
然后随着雨水降落到地面
rain will bring them down on us.
那就是3乘10的27次方颗子弹
That's three million billion trillion bullets
在...在我们的空气中
in the... in the air we breathe,
饮水中  食物中
the water we drink, the food we eat.
其中大多数子弹会持续发射一百多年
Most of these bullets will not stop firing for 100 years.
而有些会持续五万年以上
Some of them, not for 50,000 years.
好  你的顾虑
Yes, and, uh, this concern
完全基于报告中对一块石头的描述吗
stems entirely from the description of a rock?
是的
Yes.
谢比纳同志
Comrade Shcherbina...
我要你去切尔诺贝利
I want you to go to Chernobyl.
你要亲自查看反应堆
You take a look at the reactor, you personally,
然后直接向我汇报
and you report directly back to me.
明智的决定  总书记同志
A wise decision, comrade General Secretary--
带列加索夫教授一起去
And take Professor Legasov with you.
不好意思  总书记同志  但我...
Forgive me, comrade General Secretary, but I--
你懂得核反应堆的原理吗
Do you know how a nuclear reactor works?
-不懂  -不懂
- No. - No.
那你怎么能理解你所看到的情况呢
Well, then how will you know what you're looking at?
会议结束
Meeting adjourned.
核反应堆的原理是什么
How does a nuclear reactor work?
-什么  -这个问题很简单
- What? - It's a simple question.
答案一点也不简单
It's hardly a simple answer.
当然  你觉得我太笨了  听不懂
Of course, you presume I'm too stupid to understand.
那我换种说法  告诉我核反应堆的原理
So I'll restate: tell me how a nuclear reactor works,
否则我就叫士兵
or I'll have one of these
把你扔出直升机
soldiers throw you out of the helicopter.
核反应堆利用蒸汽发电
A nuclear reactor makes electricity with steam.
蒸汽推动汽轮机产生电能
The steam turns a turbine which generates electricity.
常规发电厂
Where a typical power plant
通过烧煤来产生蒸汽
makes steam by burning coal,
而核电厂...
a nuclear plant...
核电厂中会利用裂变反应
In a nuclear plant, we use something called fission.
采用一种不稳定的元素  比如铀235
We take an unstable element like uranium 235,
原子核中的中子数量过多
which has too many neutrons.
-中子就是...  -子弹
- A neutron is, uh-- - The bullet.
没错  子弹
Yes, the bullet.
子弹从铀核中射出来
So, bullets are flying off of the uranium.
然后
Now...
如果将足够多的铀原子聚集在一起
if we put enough uranium atoms close together,
来自一个原子的子弹最终会击中另一个原子
the bullets from one atom will eventually strike another atom.
撞击产生的力量会使原子分裂
The force of this impact splits that atom apart,
释放出巨大的能量  这就是裂变
releasing a tremendous amount of energy, fission.
-那石墨呢  -对
- And the graphite? - Ah, yes.
中子的速度
The neutrons are actually
实在太快了  我们称之为"通量"
traveling so fast-- we call this "flux"--
相对来说
it's relatively unlikely that
铀原子彼此击中的概率很低
the uranium atoms will ever hit one another.
在RBMK反应堆中  燃料棒被石墨包围
In RBMK reactors, we surround the fuel rods with graphite
目的是调节  减慢中子通量
to moderate, slow down, the neutron flux.
好
Good.
我明白核反应堆的原理了
I know how a nuclear reactor works.
现在不需要你了
Now I don't need you.
-帮帮我  我找不到我丈夫  -现在没空
- Can you help me? I need to find my husband. - No. Not now.
-米哈伊尔  -柳德米拉
- Mikhail! - Lyudmilla.
带她走
Take her.
带她离开这里  拜托
Take her away from here, please.
离他们远点  你想生病吗
Get away from them! You want to get sick?
快走
Go!
求求你带她离开  求求你了
Please take her, please take her.
求求你带她离开
Please take her, please.
求求你
Please! Please!
求求你带她离开
Please take her!
对不起  我是瓦西里·伊格纳滕科的妻子
Excuse me, I am Vasily Ignatenko's wife.
他是消防员  伊格纳滕科
He's a fireman. Ignatenko.
伊格纳滕科  军事第六消防和救援站的
Ignatenko, Sixth Paramilitary Fire and Rescue Unit.
我得找到他  求求你了
I need to find him. Please.
伊格纳滕科...
Ignatenko...
他要被直升机转送去莫斯科
He's being transported by helicopter to Moscow.
第六医院
Hospital number six.
为什么  他不要紧吧  我能看他吗
Why, is he all right? Can I see him?
你想见他  那去莫斯科吧
You want to see him? Go to Moscow.
但他们都不让我们离开这里
But they're not letting us leave here.
告诉他们布洛夫少校批准了
Tell them Major Burov allows it.
-他们什么时候带他走  -现在
- Oh. When are they taking him? - Now.
我们正在接近核电厂
We're approaching the power plant.
他们做了什么
What have they done?
你能看见内部吗
Can you see inside?
我不需要  看
I don't have to. Look.
房顶上就有石墨
That's graphite on the roof.
整个厂房都被炸开了
The whole building's been blown open.
堆芯已经暴露了
The core's exposed!
我不明白你怎么从这儿就能断定
I can't see how you can tell that from here.
我的天
Oh, for God's sakes.
看见那光晕了吗
Look at that glow!
那是放射线离子化空气的结果
That's radiation ionizing the air!
眼见才能为实
Well, if we can't see, we don't know.
-直接开到厂房上方去  -鲍里斯
- Get us directly over the building! - Boris,
-不许直呼我名字  -如果我们飞到...
- Don't you use my name! - if we fly...
暴露的反应堆上空  我们一周内就会死
...directly over an open reactor, we'll be dead within a week!
会死
Dead!
长官
Sir?
飞到厂房上面去  否则我枪毙你
Get us over that building, or I'll have you shot!
如果你直接飞到堆芯上方  我向你保证
If you fly directly over that core, I promise you,
明天早上  你会巴不得被枪毙
by tomorrow morning, you'll be begging for that bullet.
明斯克  白俄罗斯共产党总部
也许你最好改天再来
Perhaps if you came back another day.
太好了
Just wonderful.
格拉宁副书记
Deputy Secretary Garanin.
白俄罗斯核能源研究所的乌拉娜·霍缪克
Ulana Khomyuk of the Byelorussian Institute for Nuclear Energy.
幸会
What a pleasure.
我来介绍一下
Let me introduce--
我是为切尔诺贝利而来
I'm here about Chernobyl.
谈得太愉快了
Such a lovely time.
-尽快再来吧  -我会的  谢谢
- Visit again soon. - I will. Thank you.
我必须告诉你  这就是大家不喜欢科学家的原因
I must tell you, this is why no one likes scientists.
当我们需要治好疾病时  他们跑哪去了
When we have a disease to cure, where are they?
在实验室  埋头苦读  于是老太太就死了
In a lab, noses in their books, and so Grandma dies.
可是没事的时候
But when there isn't a problem,
他们到处跑  散布恐惧
they're everywhere, spreading fear.
我知道切尔诺贝利的事了
I know about Chernobyl.
我知道堆芯部分或全部暴露在外了
I know that the core is either partially or completely exposed.
-鬼知道那什么意思  -如果你不立即
- Whatever that means. - And that if you don't immediately
发放碘片并组织撤离整座城市
issue iodine tablets and then evacuate this city,
数十万人会罹患癌症
hundreds of thousands of people are going to get cancer,
而还不知道要死多少人
and God knows how many more will die.
非常好
Yes, very good.
切尔诺贝利确实出了事故
There has been an accident at Chernobyl,
但我被告知绝对没有问题
but I've been assured there is no problem.
我现在告诉你有问题
I'm telling you that there is.
我更倾向于我的意见
I prefer my opinion to yours.
我是核物理学家
I'm a nuclear physicist.
在你成为副书记之前
Before you were Deputy Secretary,
你在一家鞋厂工作
you worked in a shoe factory.
对  我之前确实在鞋厂工作
Yes, I worked in a shoe factory.
但现在我说了算
And now I'm in charge.
"敬全世界的工人"
"To the workers of the world."
碘片会避免你的甲状腺
Stable iodine will keep your thyroid
吸收放射性碘
from absorbing radioactive iodine.
每天服用一粒  直到吃完
Take one a day for as long as they last.
而且向东走
And go east.
离明斯克越远越好
Get as far from Minsk as you can.
做得太过火了
It's overkill.
皮卡洛夫在炫耀  为了让我们难堪
Pikalov's showing off to make us look bad.
看起来怎么样不重要
It doesn't matter how it looks.
谢比纳是个纯粹的官僚
Shcherbina is a pure bureaucrat,
他既顽固又愚蠢
as stupid as he is pigheaded.
我们用最简单的语言把真相告诉他
We'll tell him the truth in the simplest terms possible.
我们会没事的
We'll be fine.
皮卡洛夫
Pikarov!
谢比纳同志  总工程师福明
Comrade Shcherbina, Chief Engineer Fomin,
皮卡洛夫大将和我
Colonel General Pikalov, and I
为您的莅临深感荣幸
are honored at your arrival.
非常非常荣幸
Deeply, deeply honored.
当然  对于在此情况下会面我们表示遗憾
Naturally, we regret the circumstances of your visit,
但如您所见  我们正在控制损失方面
but, as you can see, we are making excellent progress
取得卓越的进展
in containing the damage.
我们已经开始对事故原因进行调查
We have begun our own inquiry into the cause of the accident,
这里是一张名单
and I have a list of individuals
写着事故的相关责任人
who we believe are accountable.
列加索夫教授  我听说
Professor Legasov, I understand
你一直在说些危险的话
you've been saying dangerous things.
非常危险
Very dangerous things.
据说我们的堆芯爆炸了
Apparently, our reactor core exploded.
请告诉我RBMK核反应堆堆芯怎么会爆炸
Please, tell me how an RBMK reactor core explodes.
我现在还无法做出解释
I'm not prepared to explain it at this time.
正如我所料  他不知道
As I presumed, he has no answer.
真是可耻  真的
It's disgraceful, really.
在这种时候散播虚假消息
To spread disinformation at a time like this.
我为什么在楼顶上看到了石墨
Why did I see graphite on the roof?
石墨只在堆芯里才有
Graphite is only found in the core,
它被用作中子通量调节剂
where it's used as a neutron flux moderator.
对吗
Correct?
福明  为什么副主席在楼顶上看到了石墨
Fomin, why did the Deputy Chairman see graphite on the roof?
这不可能
Well, that... that can't be.
谢比纳同志  抱歉  但是石墨...
Comrade Shcherbina, my apologies, but graphite...
这不可能
that's not possible.
也许你看到的是烧焦的混凝土
Perhaps you saw burnt concrete.
这你就错了
Now there you made a mistake,
因为我可能不怎么懂核反应堆
because I may not know much about nuclear reactors,
但我对混凝土很了解
but I know a lot about concrete.
-同志  我向你保证...  -我明白
- Comrade, I assure you-- - I understand.
你觉得列加索夫错了
You think Legasov is wrong.
我们怎么证明呢
How shall we prove it?
我们的大量程剂量计刚刚运到了
Our high-range dosimeter just arrived.
我们可以用铅屏蔽我们的一辆卡车
We could cover one of our trucks with lead shielding,
把剂量计装在前面
mount the dosimeter on the front.
让你的手下尽可能接近火灾现场
Have one of your men get as close to the fire as he can.
给他足够多的保护
Give him every bit of protection you have.
但记住  就算有铅屏蔽
But understand that even with lead shielding,
可能还是不够
it may not be enough.
那我就自己去
Then I'll do it myself.
很好
Good.
他回来了
He's back.
根本不是3伦琴
It's not three roentgen.
是15000伦琴
It's 15,000.
谢比纳同志
Comrade Shcherbina--
这个数值意味着什么
What does that number mean?
意味着堆芯炸开了
It means the core is open.
意味着我们肉眼可见的火灾
It means the fire we're watching with our own eyes
比广岛原子弹释放的辐射
is giving off nearly twice the radiation
要高出将近两倍
released by the bomb in Hiroshima.
那还是每个小时的量
And that's every single hour.
一小时接一小时  爆炸已经过了20小时了
Hour after hour, 20 hours since the explosion,
现在已是40颗原子弹的当量了
so 40 bombs worth by now.
明天又再加48颗
Forty-eight more tomorrow.
而且它不会停下  一周或一个月后都不会停
And it will not stop. Not in a week, not in a month.
它会一直燃烧  扩散有害物质
It will burn and spread its poison
直到整个大陆都完蛋
until the entire continent is dead.
请护送布卡诺夫同志和福明同志
Please escort Comrades Bryukhanov and Fomin
到当地的党总部去
to the local party headquarters.
-谢谢你们的服务  -同志...
- Thank you for your service. - Comrade--
你们可以走了
You're excused.
是迪亚特洛夫负责的
Dyatlov was in charge.
是迪亚特洛夫
It was Dyatlov!
-告诉我怎么扑灭  -我们用直升机
- Tell me how to put it out. - We'll use helicopters.
像灭林火那样浇水
We'll drop water on it like a forest fire.
不行  你不明白
No, no. You don't understand.
这不是火灾
This isn't a fire.
这是个裂变中的反应堆堆芯
This is a fissioning reactor core
以超过两千度的高温燃烧
burning at over 2,000 degrees.
热量会瞬间将水汽化...
The heat will instantly vaporize the water--
那我们如何扑灭
How do we put it out?
你所面临的是
You are dealing with something
这个星球上从没发生过的灾难
that has never occurred on this planet before.
硼
Boron.
硼和沙子
Boron and sand.
尽管那会产生其他的问题
Well, that'll create problems of its own,
但我...我不知道还有什么办法
but I-I don't see any other way.
当然了  需要成千上万次的投放
Of course, it's going to take thousands of drops,
因为你不能把直升机开到堆芯正上方去
because you can't fly the helicopters directly over the core,
所有多数投放物会偏离目标
so most of it is going to miss.
-要多少硼和沙子  -我没法...
- How much sand and boron? - Well, I can't be--
-老天  大概就行了  -五千吨
- For God's sake, roughly! - Five thousand tons.
而且  显然我们要疏散一大片区域
And obviously, we're going to need to evacuate an enormous area--
不用管那个  集中精力灭火
Never mind that. Focus on the fire.
我是在集中精力灭火
I am focusing on the fire.
风正卷着所有的烟
The wind, it's carrying all that smoke,
所有的放射性物质扩散
all that radiation.
至少疏散普里皮亚季  离这儿只有三公里
At least evacuate Pripyat. It's three kilometers away.
-那事由我决定  -那就决定吧
- That's my decision to make. - Then make it.
-我被命令不能疏散  -你到底是不是...
- I've been told not to. - Is it or is not--
这里我负责
I'm in charge here!
如果你只和我讲你明白的事情
This will go much easier if you talk to me
而不要谈你不明白的事的话
about the things you do understand
那一切都会简单得多
and not about the things you do not understand.
你去哪
Where are you going?
我去给你调五千吨沙袋和硼
I'm going to get you 5,000 tons of sand and boron.
有家酒店
There's a hotel.
我想用那个杯子
I'd prefer one of those.
是迷信吗
Superstitious?
莫斯科来的
Moscow?
你是为火灾来的吗
Are you here because of the fire?
有什么我们需要担心的吗
Anything we should be worried about?
没有
No.
4月27日  上午
爆炸发生30小时后
我们就位了  接近投放点
We're in position. Approaching drop.
开始
Clear to proceed.
收到  我们会一架一架地轮流投放
Copy. We'll go one by one in rotation.
提醒他们注意距离限制
Remind them about the perimeter.
他们不能直接飞到火焰上方去
They cannot fly directly over the fire.
至少保持10米距离
A minimum of a ten-meter perimeter.
10米距离  收到
Ten meter perimeter. Copy.
L1  准备投放  至少10米距离
Lead one, err preflight, maintain minimum ten-meter perimeter.
收到
Copy that.
40米...35米...
Forty meters... 35...
30米...
30...
不行  他们飞得太近了
No, no, no! They're too close!
他们不能飞到火焰上方  那要怎么...
They can't get over the fire. How are they supposed--
只能让风吹过去
The wind will have to carry it.
告诉他们  他们不能飞到堆芯上
Tell them, they cannot go over the core.
L1太近了
Lead One is too close.
我重复一遍  他们太近了
I repeat, they are too close.
收到
Copy.
L1  你已经飞进危险距离内了
Lead One, you are inside the perimeter.
没有收到  信号不良
Did not copy. Signal's breaking up.
L1
Lead One?
你收到了吗
Do you copy?
L1  你收到了吗
Lead One, do you copy?
L1  请回话
Lead One, come in.
你收到了吗  L1
Do you copy, Lead One?
L1
Lead One!
长官  我怎么指挥其他人
Sir? What do I tell the others?
还有别的办法吗  列加索夫
Is there any other way, Legasov?
派下一架飞机进去
Send the next one in.
告诉他们从西边靠近
Tell them to approach from the west.
莫斯科  库尔恰托夫原子能研究所
库尔恰托夫原子能研究所第四实验室
Kurchatov Institute Laboratory Four.
玛丽娜·古泽斯卡亚
Marina Gruzinskaya,
我是明斯克的乌拉娜·霍缪克
it's Ulana Khomyuk from Minsk.
是的  你能打电话来真是太好了
Oh, yes, how nice of you to phone.
-我们很久没联系了  -没错
- It's been too long. - It has.
我打电话是想问问我们的朋友
I was actually calling about our friend.
-就是在乡下的那个  -当然
- You know, the one in the country. - Oh, yes, of course.
我想问问他现在怎么样  那里现在好热
I wanted to see how he's doing. It's so hot there right now.
是的  非常热
Yes, it's extremely hot,
但是他的侄子们正要飞过去
but his nephews are flying down,
他们总是可以让天气凉爽下来
and they always bring cool weather.
是吗  哪个侄子
Oh? Which nephews?
暗指元素硅[Si]和硼[Bo]
分别排在元素周期表的第14位和第5位
西姆卡  14岁  小鲍里斯  5岁
Simka, who's 14, and little Boris, who's five.
太好了
Well, that's wonderful.
不过孩子爬在你身上时
Though children can make you even hotter
会让你觉得更热
when they're crawling all over you.
也许我应该去看看他们
Maybe I should visit them.
不用了  他们不欢迎访客
No, they don't want visitors.
对不起  我得回去工作了
I'm sorry, um, I have to get back to work.
我现在很忙  再见
It's very busy right now. Goodbye.
他们在往火上投放沙子和硼
They're dropping sand and boron on the fire.
要我也会那么做
It's what I would do.
没错  我想也是
Yes, I'm sure it is.
你要去哪里
Where are you going?
切尔诺贝利
Chernobyl.
一切都很顺利  二十次投放
It's been smooth. Twenty drops.
怎么了
What?
这个城市有五万人
There are 50,000 people in this city.
伊林教授  委员会成员之一
Professor Ilyin, who's also on the commission,
他说这点辐射用不着疏散
says the radiation isn't high enough to evacuate.
伊林不是物理学家
Ilyin isn't a physicist.
他是个医生
Well, he's a medical doctor.
如果他说安全  那就安全
If he says it's safe, it's safe.
但他们留在这儿就不安全
Not if they stay here.
我们就留在这里
We're staying here.
没错  所以我们活不过五年
Yes, we are, and we'll be dead in five years.
对不起  我
I'm sorry, I...
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
我是谢比纳
Shcherbina.
谢谢
Thank you.
瑞典的一座核电站检测到了辐射
A nuclear plant in Sweden has detected radiation
并分辨出是我们燃料的副产品
and identified it as a byproduct of our fuel.
美国人拍了卫星照片
The Americans took satellite photos.
反应堆建筑  烟雾  还有火灾
The reactor building, the smoke, the fire.
全世界都知道了
The whole world knows.
风一直吹向德国
The wind has been blowing toward Germany.
法兰克福  已经禁止孩子们
They're not letting children play outside...
去外面玩
in Frankfurt.
想抽烟吗
Want a smoke?
苏联境内发生了一起核事故
There has been a nuclear accident in the Soviet Union
苏联也承认消息属实
and the Soviets have admitted that it happened.
苏联方面称
The Soviet version is this.
核事故
基辅市附近
One of the atomic reactors
切尔诺贝利核电站内一处反应堆受损
at the Chernobyl Atomic Power Plant near the city of Kiev was damaged,
莫斯科有推断称
and there is speculation in Moscow
可能已有人受伤甚至死亡
that people were injured and may have died.
苏联如此痛快地承认了事故的发生
The Soviets may have been fairly quick to acknowledge the accident
4月27日  下午2点
爆炸发生36小时后
可能是因为证据已以轻微核辐射的形式
because evidence in the form of mild nuclear radiation
穿越了苏联边界  到达斯堪的纳维亚
had already reached beyond the Soviet borders to Scandinavia.
请注意  请注意
尊敬的同志们
城市人民委员会通知大家
普里皮亚季市附近的
切尔诺贝利市核电站
发生了紧急辐射事件
为了确保人民安全
目前正在进行必要的临时撤离
撤离至基辅州的居民点
为此  每座居民楼下
就在今天  4月27日
从14时起
将会有车辆接送居民
随行人员包括警察和政府工作人员
建议携带重要文件和必需品
以及最重要的食物
相关领导  公司和机构的代表
会留下维持城市的基本运转
撤离期间
所有居民楼将被警察征用
同志们  临走前不要忘记
关闭门窗  关闭水电气
请遵守秩序和临时撤离安全规定
请注意  请注意
尊敬的同志们
城市人民委员会通知大家
普里皮亚季市附近的
切尔诺贝利市核电站
我说了掉头  这里是禁区
I said turn around. This is a restricted zone.
我来自白俄罗斯核能源研究所
I'm from the Byelorussian Institute for Nuclear Energy.
你有许可吗
Do you have permission?
听着  事情紧急  我得找人谈谈
Listen to me, I need to speak to someone urgently.
马上掉头  要不然我就逮捕你
Turn around right now, or I'll arrest you.
如果你要逮捕我
If you arrest me,
就带我去见最高负责人
you should take me to the highest possible authority.
我们需要展开放射性调查
We have to start a radiological survey.
一个区一个区的来  徒步  手持剂量仪
Sector by sector, on foot, dosimeters in hand.
你还好吗
Are you all right?
当然
Of course.
同志们
Comrades--
警卫在南部检查点逮捕了这个女人
The guards arrested this woman at the south checkpoint.
我本该把她关进牢房
I'd have put her in a cell--
但是他觉得你们应该知道我都知道了
But he thought you should know that I know.
我知道你们的反应堆芯爆炸了
I know that your reactor core is exposed.
我知道石墨着火了  燃料正在熔化
I know the graphite is on fire, the fuel is melting,
以及你们在反应堆上方投放沙子和硼
and you're dropping sand and boron on it,
你们可能觉得这很明智  但你们犯了个错
which you probably thought was smart, but you've made a mistake.
乌拉娜·尤里伊芙娜·霍缪克  首席物理学家
Ulana Yuriyvna Khomyuk, Chief Physicist,
就职于白俄罗斯核能源研究所
Byelorussian Institute for Nuclear Energy.
你是瓦列利·阿列克谢维奇·列加索夫吗
And you are Valery Alexeyevich Legasov?
覆盖堆芯的确能灭火
Smothering the core will put the fire out,
但是最终  温度还是会增加到
but the temperature will eventually increase--
相信我  我很清楚
Believe me, I'm perfectly aware.
但我估计至少需要一个月
But I estimate at least a month
堆芯才会熔穿下部的混凝土层
before it melts through the lower concrete pad,
-这能给我们时间  -不  没有一个月
- which gives us time-- - No, you don't have a month.
大约只有两天
You have approximately two days.
的确  燃料需要一个月的时间
Yes, the fuel would take a month
才能到达这里的混凝土层
to reach the concrete pad here.
但是首先  在周二之前
But first... it's going to burn through
就会熔穿这里的生物屏障
the biological shield here by Tuesday.
一旦熔穿  燃料就会进入这些水箱
And when it does, it's going to hit these tanks--
起泡池  蓄水池
bubbler pools, reservoirs--
应急冷却系统的蓄水池  我理解你的担忧
Reservoirs for the ECS. I understand your concern,
但是我得到了工厂员工的证实
but I confirmed it with plant personnel.
-水箱基本上都空了  -不  之前是空的
- The tanks are nearly empty. - No, they were nearly empty.
所有这些点  这里  这里  还有这里
Each of these points here, here, and here
都将水排放至起泡池
all drain to the bubbler pools.
我猜核电站里的管道应该已经全部破裂
I'm guessing that every pipe in the building ruptured.
加上我来时看到的那些消防车
And then there are those fire engines that I saw on the way in.
消防软管还连着呢
The fire hoses are still connected.
他们一直都在向建筑物喷水
They've been gushing water into the structure this whole time.
水箱是满的
The tanks are full.
苏联中央电视台
据苏联内阁公布的消息
切尔诺贝利核电站发生了一起事故
一处核反应堆受损
目前正在采取措施解决事故带来的问题
受害群众得到了援助
政府已成立委员会调查
我只有十分钟时间  然后又得接着打电话
I have ten minutes, then I'm back on the phone
向所有的友国致歉
apologizing to our friends,
向我们的敌国致歉
apologizing to our enemies.
我们的力量取决于自我认知
Our power comes from the perception of our power.
你们明白这次事故造成了多大损失吗
Do you understand the damage this has done?
你们明白这事关多么重大吗
Do you understand what's at stake?
鲍里斯
Boris.
列加索夫教授将进行汇报
Professor Legasov will deliver our briefing.
有好消息
There is some good news.
空投在有效地减小火势
The air drops are working to douse the fire.
放射性核素排放量也有所减少
There's been a reduction in radionuclide emissions,
但火还要至少两周
but the fire will not be extinguished
才能被灭掉
for at least another two weeks.
另外还有一个问题
There is also an additional problem.
核燃料就算没着火
Nuclear fuel doesn't turn cold
也不会冷却下来
simply because it is not on fire.
事实上  其温度有可能会上升
In fact, the temperature will likely rise
因为我们投放了一层沙子
as a result of the blanket of sand we've dropped.
铀会熔化沙子
The uranium will melt the sand,
形成熔岩
creating a kind of lava
熔掉下面的保护屏障
which will begin to melt down through the shield below.
你制造了熔岩
You have made lava?
这在预料之中
I anticipated this.
我本以为有足够的时间来加固
I believed there was time to reinforce
下面的混凝土保护层
this lower concrete pad
避免熔岩侵入地下
before the lava reached the earth
污染地下水
and contaminated the groundwater.
但事实证明  我考虑错了方向
But as it turned out, I was worried about the wrong thing.
因为我本以为反应堆下面的
It was my understanding that these large water tanks
大型水箱几乎是空的
under the reactor were essentially empty.
这位是白俄罗斯核能源研究所的乌拉娜·霍缪克
This is Ulana Khomyuk of the Byelorussian Institute.
多亏了她  我们意识到
Thanks to her insight, we are now aware
水箱现在其实是满的
that the tanks are, in fact, full.
装满了水而已  这有什么问题吗  教授
Of water. Why is that a problem, professor?
当熔岩进入这些水箱
When the lava enters these tanks,
水会立即过热并蒸发
it will instantly superheat and vaporize
水箱一共有约七千立方米的水
approximately 7,000 cubic meters of water,
这会引起严重的热爆炸
causing a significant thermal explosion.
有多严重
How significant?
相当于200到400万顿TNT炸药威力
我们估计约为两到四百万吨级
We estimate between two and four megatons.
半径三十公里内的所有东西
Everything within a 30-kilometer radius
都将被完全摧毁
will be completely destroyed,
包括切尔诺贝利剩下的三个反应堆
including the three remaining reactors at Chernobyl.
而堆芯中的所有放射性物质
The entirety of the radioactive material in all of the cores
都将被喷射出来
will be ejected at force
被巨大的冲击扩散开
and dispersed by a massive shock wave,
最远至大约两百公里外
which will extend approximately 200 kilometers
可能对整个基辅地区及明斯克部分地区人民
and likely be fatal to the entire population of Kiev
造成致命性伤害
as well as a portion of Minsk.
核辐射的释放量非常巨大
The release of radiation will be severe
将影响整个苏联乌克兰
and will impact all of Soviet Ukraine,
拉脱维亚  立陶宛  白俄罗斯
Latvia, Lithuania, Byelorussia,
以及波兰  捷克斯洛伐克  匈牙利
as well as Poland, Czechoslovakia, Hungary,
罗马尼亚和东德大部分地区
Romania, and most of East Germany.
怎么个影响法
What do you mean "impact"?
对于大部分地区  几乎会永久破坏
For much of the area, a nearly permanent disruption
食物和水的供应
of the food and water supply,
癌症和出生缺陷率急剧上升
a steep increase in the rates of cancer and birth defects.
我不知道具体的死亡数量  但肯定会很多
I don't know how many deaths there will be, but many.
对于白俄罗斯和乌克兰来说
For Byelorussia and the Ukraine,
影响意味着该地区至少一百年
"impact" means completely uninhabitable
完全不适合人类居住
for a minimum of 100 years.
有超过五千万人
There are more than 50 million people
居住在白俄罗斯和乌克兰
living in Byelorussia and Ukraine.
六千万人  是的
Sixty, yes.
我们还有多少时间
And how long before this happens?
大约48到72小时
Approximately 48 to 72 hours.
但是我们也许有办法
But we may have a solution.
我们能抽出水箱中的水
We can pump the water from the tanks.
但是水箱被阀门封死了
Unfortunately, the tanks are sealed shut by a sluice gate,
只能从管道系统内部
and the gate can only be opened manually
手动开启
from within the duct system itself.
所以我们需要三名工人
So we need to find three plant workers
了解工厂内部的工人
who know the facility well enough
进入地下区域
to enter the basement here,
顺着管道系统
find their way through all these duct ways,
来到这边的阀门
get to the sluice gate valve here,
好让我们抽干水箱
and give us the access we need to pump out the tanks.
当然了  我们还需要你的允许
Of course, we will need your permission.
我的什么允许
My permission for what?
管道中的水
Uh, the water in these ducts,
污染等级很高...
the level of radioactive contamination--
他们很可能一周后就会死亡
They'll likely be dead in a week.
我们需要你的允许  杀死三个人
We're asking for your permission to kill three men.
列加索夫同志
Comrade Legasov...
所有胜利都有不可避免的代价
all victories inevitably come at a cost.
4月28日  上午9点30分
爆炸发生56小时后
然后打开这里的...水阀
And open the sluice gate valve... here.
水阀很难操作
The valve will be difficult to operate,
所以我们需要三名工人
so we'll need three men
熟知地下区域构造的工人
who will need to know the basement layout.
当然了  自愿的人会有重赏
And, of course, any volunteers will be rewarded.
每年四百卢布的津贴
A yearly stipend of 400 rubles.
如果是本来就在一号和二号反应堆
And, uh, for those of you working in reactors
工作的人  还能得到提拔
one and two, promotions.
为什么一号和二号反应堆还在工作
Why are reactors one and two still operating at all?
我的朋友是那晚的保安
My friend was a security guard that night,
她现在快死了
and, uh, she's now dying.
我们也都听说了那些消防员的事
And we've all heard about the firemen.
现在你要我们游到一个燃烧着的反应堆下方
And now you want us to swim underneath a burning reactor?
你知道污染有多重吗
Do you even know how contaminated it is?
我...我给不出具体的数字
I... I don't have an exact number.
不需要具体数字也知道这会要了我们的命
You don't need an exact number to know if it'll kill us.
但你甚至都不敢告诉我们
But you can't even tell us that.
我们为什么要这么做  为了四百卢布吗
Why should we do this? For what, 400 rubles?
你们要这么做是因为别无选择
You'll do it because it must be done.
因为其他人都做不到
you'll do it, because nobody else can.
否则会有上百万人死去
And if you don't, millions will die.
如果你们说这个理由还不够  我不信
If you tell me that's not enough, I won't believe you.
这是我们民族一向不同于其他人的地方
This is what has always set our people apart.
我们血液中流淌千年的牺牲精神
A thousand years of sacrifice in our veins.
每一代人必须面对他们的苦难
And every generation must know its own suffering.
我唾弃这起事故的元凶
I spit on the people who did this,
我诅咒我需要付出的代价
and I curse the price I have to pay.
但我在接受事实
But I'm making my peace with it,
现在轮到你们了
and now you make yours.
游到那水下
And go into that water.
因为必须有人去做
Because it must be done.
安纳楠科
Ananenko.
拜兹帕罗夫
Bezpalov.
巴拉诺夫
Baranov.